<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-18T20:11:06-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Michael Black Made</title><entry><title type="html">Booze Shelf</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Booze Shelf" /><published>2025-01-05T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf.html"><![CDATA[<p>When Kid became mobile, we had to ditch our bar cart and temporarily stash our booze on the floor of a closet. An obviously horrible location, as it was treacherous to store other things in the closet around and on top of the bottles, and we could never remember what we had.</p>

<p>Recently inspiration struck when looking at a bare patch of wall, and now we have a new booze shelf!</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/booze_shelf/booze_shelf.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/booze_shelf/booze_shelf_mid.jpg" alt="booze shelf" /></a></p>

<p>We’d talked about doing a two-tiered set of shelves in the corner of the dining room, but the stud locations and tight quarters meant we’d need custom brackets. It was too much start up energy and the project idea languished.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/booze_shelf/cardboard_mockup.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/booze_shelf/cardboard_mockup_mid.jpg" alt="cardboard_mockup" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Longheld vision in cardboard</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The design north star had been this photo my wife sent me from <a href="https://aglassofbovino.com/2020/06/main-bathroom-one-room-challenge-the-reveal-spring-2020/">A Glass of Bovino</a>:</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/booze_shelf/inspo.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/booze_shelf/inspo_mid.jpg" alt="shelf inspo" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Love the brass; love the chamfer</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>While we’ve found brass brackets we like for most other shelves in the house, they’re expensive, and this one is tucked out of the way so keeping things cheap seemed ideal. Shelf and bracket are simply the IKEA <a href="https://www.ikea.com/us/en/p/bergshult-ramshult-wall-shelf-white-s99325477/">BERGSHULT / RAMSHULT combo</a>.</p>

<p>But what was necessary to take from the inspo was the railing. Railing allows the full surface of the shelf to be used without fear of bottles falling onto your head. Instead of tracking down fancy museum railing, I thought it would be simple to just make my own. I ordered some <a href="https://www.onlinemetals.com/en/buy/brass/0-1875-brass-round-bar-360-h02-extruded/pid/4345">3/16” brass round bar</a> from onlinemetals.com, then cut it down into small segments on the bandsaw and rounded the cut ends on the belt sander. I bent them into U shapes with a metal bender, and sanded them shiny with steel wool. Tight fitting holes were drilled half of the depth into the shelf and the railings were able to press fit in place.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="home improvement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When Kid became mobile, we had to ditch our bar cart and temporarily stash our booze on the floor of a closet. An obviously horrible location, as it was treacherous to store other things in the closet around and on top of the bottles, and we could never remember what we had.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/images/booze_shelf/booze_shelf_thumb.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/images/booze_shelf/booze_shelf_thumb.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Now Playing</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/23/now-playing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Now Playing" /><published>2023-11-23T14:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T14:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/23/now-playing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/23/now-playing.html"><![CDATA[<p>We needed somewhere to place the sleeve for the currently-playing record. We had an IKEA picture ledge from our old apartment that just needed to be hung up. But before we got around to it, my wife came to me and mused: “Most of the time I’m listening to the radio, and I’d love to see the name of the song or artist without having to pull out my phone. Can you put a ticker of the live feed on the front of the shelf?”</p>

<p>It took less than 30 minutes to report an excited “yes!”</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/prototype.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/prototype_mid.jpg" alt="prototype" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>It's almost embarassing when the Seattle station plays Nirvana</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Our fabulous local radio station, <a href="https://kexp.org/">KEXP</a>, has a real time playlist you can query through their API. I grabbed a microcontroller, a screen, and some other bits I had on hand, and threw together a working prototype. Knowing I had some scrap wood, I decided it would be a fun constraint to build this without buying anything new.</p>

<p>Two boards were joined into a T, making a shelf with a lip to hold up the record and a face to mount the screen into. I cut a slot in the face board that the shelf board could press-fit into using a table saw.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/wood.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/wood_mid.jpg" alt="wood" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Press-fit slot cut with table saw</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/wood_with_screen.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/wood_with_screen_mid.jpg" alt="wood with screen" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Getting a feel for it in place</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>A few features added in were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A switch on the front to turn the screen on and off</li>
  <li>A hidden reed switch on the shelf to detect when it was holding a record.</li>
  <li>Two LEDs on the front which turn on when a record is detected</li>
  <li>A hidden contrast knob for the LCD</li>
  <li>The words “NOW PLAYING” etched into the wood</li>
</ul>

<p>I used a router to cut a recess so the LCD would sit flush against the front, then got everything except the front LEDs mounted, wired, and working.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/first_assembly.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/first_assembly_mid.jpg" alt="first assembly" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>I should figure out how to work with ribbon cables...</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>A friend offered to use his laser to etch the front, so we gave it a shot. This was a new technique for us, and we learned a lot about the machine and how to interact with cheap wood. In hindsight I don’t think the fill pattern works as well with the wood grain as perhaps just an outline would have.</p>

<p>I then stained the wood, glued and reassembled everything, and installed the LEDs on either side of the etched words.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/stain_and_laser.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/stain_and_laser_mid.jpg" alt="laser-etched" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Stained and laser-etched</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/stained_side.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/stained_side_mid.jpg" alt="stained side view" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Electronics are hidden from normal viewing angles</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/reed_switch.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/reed_switch_mid.jpg" alt="reed switch" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The hidden reed switch that a record presses down on</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I did unfortunately have to go buy brackets to mount this to the wall, which sadly brought the project cost up to $4. So close!</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/brackets.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/brackets_mid.jpg" alt="brackets" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The single center bracket I first tried was too bouncy</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>And that’s it!</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/with_record.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/with_record_mid.jpg" alt="with record" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Holding a record</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/with_radio.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/with_radio_mid.jpg" alt="with radio" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Showing what's on the radio</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>It’s simultaneously exactly what we need while also being pretty rough and clunky. I don’t love the screen, the etching looks dull, and the front LEDs are totally unnecessary. But it was fun to build, and it was a great way to use up some parts that would otherwise just collect dust.</p>

<p>The code is here if you’re interested: <a href="https://github.com/brushyfork23/now-playing/blob/main/now_playing.ino">github.com/brushyfork23/now-playing</a>. I wrote it quickly and never looked back, so it’s missing some key features. Overflowing text doesn’t scroll into view, and there’s some encoding mismatch so characters are often garbled. But it works well enough to answer the question “who’s playing?”</p>

<p>PS: the old picture ledge we had from our last apartment? I repurposed it and its brethren to hold shallow items in the garage.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/images/now_playing/garage_shelves.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/now_playing/garage_shelves_mid.jpg" alt="garage shelves" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Perfect size for glue and paint!</figcaption>
    
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="home improvement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We needed somewhere to place the sleeve for the currently-playing record. We had an IKEA picture ledge from our old apartment that just needed to be hung up. But before we got around to it, my wife came to me and mused: “Most of the time I’m listening to the radio, and I’d love to see the name of the song or artist without having to pull out my phone. Can you put a ticker of the live feed on the front of the shelf?”]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/images/now_playing/now_playing_thumb.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/images/now_playing/now_playing_thumb.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>