<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-29T10:59:46-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Michael Black Made</title><entry><title type="html">Page Turner</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/08/25/page-turner.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Page Turner" /><published>2025-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/08/25/page-turner</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/08/25/page-turner.html"><![CDATA[<figure class="video">
    <video controls="" preload="metadata" poster="">
        <source src="/assets/page_turner/page_turner.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
        <source src="/assets/page_turner/page_turner.webm" type="video/webm" />
        <p>
            Your browser doesn't support HTML video. Here is a
            <a href="/assets/page_turner/page_turner.mp4" download="/assets/page_turner/page_turner.mp4">link to the video</a> instead.
        </p>
    </video>
    
</figure>

<p>Bodies are cool, but finicky, and sometimes they don’t do what we want. A friend of mine has some unexplained nerve pain in their hands, and it hurts for them to type on a keyboard or swipe on a touchscreen. At their request, I made them a device which connects wirelessly to an iPad and reads their waved hand gestures to touchlessly navigate pages in an e-book, allowing for pain-free reading. I built this page turner from some electronic parts from Adafruit and a 3D printed enclosure.</p>

<p>A search for “gesture sensor” introduced me to Adafruit’s <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/3595">APDS-9960 breakout board</a>. I wanted the page turner to be small and portable, so it can travel conveniently with the e-reader, so I selected the smallest microcontroller package and battery I wanted to work with: the <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/5700">QT Py S3</a> (an ESP32-S3 breakout) with a <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/5397">charger BFF</a> and a <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/3898">400mAh lipo</a>. These all interconnect with JST cables, so all that needed soldering were some pin headers and an extra wire for the APDS-9960’s interrupt pin. The interrupt connection could be skipped, but it helps improve battery life by not requiring the QT Py to constantly poll the sensor.</p>

<h2 id="assembly">Assembly</h2>

<p>I cut a wire ~1.5” long and soldered it between the QT Py’s A3 and the sensor’s INT.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/page_turner/int_wire.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/int_wire_mid.jpg" alt="interrupt wire" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Note that the wire enters through the back of each board.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I soldered pin headers onto the QT Py, skipping over A3,</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/pin_headers.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/pin_headers_mid.jpg" alt="pin headers" /></a></p>

<p>then finally soldered the charger BFF to those headers.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/charger_attached.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/charger_attached_mid.jpg" alt="charger attached" /></a></p>

<p>The components were connected together via JST cables and the wires were carefully bent into shape to scrunch everything into the right orientations.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/jst_attached.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/jst_attached_mid.jpg" alt="JST cables" /></a></p>

<p>I outsourced enclosure design to a friend who came up with this phenomenal first model:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/first_model.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/first_model_mid.jpg" alt="first model" /></a></p>

<p>A cap fits over the charger BFF’s onboard power switch to make it usable through the enclosure.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/switch_cap.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/switch_cap_mid.jpg" alt="switch cap" /></a></p>

<p>A light pipe, printed from translucent PCTG, brings the light of the status LED from the QT Py around to the same side as the switch.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/light_pipe.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/light_pipe_mid.jpg" alt="light pipe" /></a></p>

<p>The battery charge indicator simply shines up through a hole.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/charging.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/charging_mid.jpg" alt="charging" /></a></p>

<p>Some heat-set inserts were pressed in with a soldering iron to let the enclosure screw together. A spare pair on the back could be used to mount a clip, so the device could be clipped onto the side of the e-reader itself.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/inserts.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/inserts_mid.jpg" alt="heat set inserts" /></a></p>

<p>The completed page turner:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/page_turner.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/page_turner_mid.jpg" alt="page turner" /></a></p>

<h2 id="software">Software</h2>

<p>The software for this project ended up relatively simple. You can check it out at <a href="http://github.com/brushyfork23/page_turner">github.com/brushyfork23/page_turner</a>.</p>

<p>Originally I had configured a right-to-left swipe to advance the page and a left-to-right swipe to go back, but some real world testing revealed that you mostly only want to go forward and it’s tiring to swing your hand back around the sensor. I changed from gesture sensing to simple proximity sensing, and now the device can be used in any orientation by passing a finger back and forth.</p>

<p>Basic battery monitoring is done by a scan at startup and the device flashes green, orange, or red to indicate the charge percentage remaining.</p>

<h2 id="struggles">Struggles</h2>

<p>The part of the enclosure where the sensor meets the face took a lot of iteration, because if there was any gap between the sensor and the enclosure aperture then the IR LED would flood the inside of the case and cause false positives.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/page_turner/sensor.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/sensor_mid.jpg" alt="final sensor" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The final working design.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>When I started this project, I didn’t have my own 3D printer, so each iteration required finding time on another available friend’s machine. It was impossible to adjust for the sensor gap because the tolerances of each person’s printer were different, so I finally decided I was ready and purchased my own. I bought a <a href="https://www.prusa3d.com/product/prusa-core-one-kit/">Prusa Core One</a> and some <a href="https://www.3dfuel.com/collections/1-75mm-pro-pctg/products/pro-pctg-ocean-blue-1-75mm">Pro PCTG filament from 3D-Fuel</a>, and was printing with fantastic results right away once I configured <a href="https://support.3dfuel.com/hc/en-us/articles/22046343945495-Pro-PCTG-Print-Profiles">3D-Fuel’s print profiles</a>.</p>

<p>Having a printer allowed me to experiment with true rapid prototyping. I printed the specific section of the model I was having trouble with and iterated on it alone, using only a gram or so of filament each time and only taking 5 minutes between versions. A month of failed back-and-forth was solved in just a few hours!</p>

<p><a href="/assets/page_turner/iterations.jpg"><img src="/assets/page_turner/iterations_mid.jpg" alt="sensor iterations" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Gesture sensor for pain-free reading]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/page_turner/page_turner.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/page_turner/page_turner.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Booze Shelf</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Booze Shelf" /><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2025/01/05/booze-shelf.html"><![CDATA[<p>When Kid became mobile, we had to ditch our bar cart and temporarily stash our booze on the floor of a closet. An obviously horrible location, as it was treacherous to store other things in the closet around and on top of the bottles, and we could never remember what we had.</p>

<p>Recently inspiration struck when looking at a bare patch of wall, and now we have a new booze shelf!</p>

<p><a href="/assets/booze_shelf/booze_shelf.jpg"><img src="/assets/booze_shelf/booze_shelf_mid.jpg" alt="booze shelf" /></a></p>

<p>We’d talked about doing a two-tiered set of shelves in the corner of the dining room, but the stud locations and tight quarters meant we’d need custom brackets. It was too much start up energy and the project idea languished.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/booze_shelf/cardboard_mockup.jpg"><img src="/assets/booze_shelf/cardboard_mockup_mid.jpg" alt="cardboard mockup" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Longheld vision in cardboard</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The design north star had been this photo my wife sent me from <a href="https://aglassofbovino.com/2020/06/main-bathroom-one-room-challenge-the-reveal-spring-2020/">A Glass of Bovino</a>:</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/booze_shelf/inspo.jpg"><img src="/assets/booze_shelf/inspo_mid.jpg" alt="shelf inspo" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Love the brass; love the chamfer</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>While we’ve found brass brackets we like for most other shelves in the house, they’re expensive, and this one is tucked out of the way so keeping things cheap seemed ideal. Shelf and bracket are simply the IKEA <a href="https://www.ikea.com/us/en/p/bergshult-ramshult-wall-shelf-white-s99325477/">BERGSHULT / RAMSHULT combo</a>.</p>

<p>But what was necessary to take from the inspo was the railing. Railing allows the full surface of the shelf to be used without fear of bottles falling onto your head. Instead of tracking down fancy museum railing, I thought it would be simple to just make my own. I ordered some <a href="https://www.onlinemetals.com/en/buy/brass/0-1875-brass-round-bar-360-h02-extruded/pid/4345">3/16” brass round bar</a> from onlinemetals.com, then cut it down into small segments on the bandsaw and rounded the cut ends on the belt sander. I bent them into U shapes with a metal bender, and sanded them shiny with steel wool. Tight fitting holes were drilled half of the depth into the shelf and the railings were able to press fit in place.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I cut and bent some brass into little railings for a shelf to hold our booze.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/booze_shelf/booze_shelf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/booze_shelf/booze_shelf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">LOVE Music Box</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/12/24/love-music-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LOVE Music Box" /><published>2024-12-24T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/12/24/love-music-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/12/24/love-music-box.html"><![CDATA[<figure class="video">
    <video controls="" preload="metadata" poster="">
        <source src="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
        <source src="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.webm" type="video/webm" />
        <p>
            Your browser doesn't support HTML video. Here is a
            <a href="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.mp4" download="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.mp4">link to the video</a> instead.
        </p>
    </video>
    
</figure>

<blockquote>
  <p>L is for the way you look at me.<br />
O is for the only one I see.<br />
V is very, very extraordinary.<br />
E is even more than anyone that you adore can.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In Nat King Cole’s classic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gZYtes1RO_w">L-O-V-E</a> the two sung verses are separated by an instrumental verse with a trumpet solo. I thought it would be fun to build a music box where each letter’s section could be swapped between the vocal and instrumental renditions.</p>

<p>My idea was to make letter-shaped blocks which could be placed on a base with a play button and speaker. If a slot is filled then that letter is sung, and if it’s empty then the trumpet plays.</p>

<p>I attempted this a few years ago, but was stopped by the difficulty of splitting the audio apart. I couldn’t figure out how to get the divisions exactly right and worried that someone would notice. I let the perfect be the enemy of the <del>good</del> done. But recently (and in large part thanks to watching makers <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@laurakampf">Laura Kampf</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@felixschelhasse">Felix Schelhasse</a>) I’ve begun to embrace the acceptance of imperfection. I decided to be brave and give it another try.</p>

<p>I’d been wanting to make a gift for my wonderful wife, and this project felt like a great fit. We met and bonded over a love of music, and she’s a big fan of any song with a brass section. However, knowing that it’s for her adds some pressure. She deserves something gorgeous, which means I’ll need to step up the quality of my materials and approach. Plastic parts aren’t going to cut it; the base will be a hardwood box and the letters should stand beautiful on their own.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/wood.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/wood_mid.jpg" alt="walnut lumber" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Baby's first Walnut</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I went to <a href="http://www.crosscutseattle.com/">Crosscut Hardwoods</a> and asked for some guidance, and they kindly helped me find this nice piece of Walnut. This board would become the box, but I wanted the blocks to be thicker so I grabbed a chunk of oak from the off-cuts bin.</p>

<p>I searched through the fonts in Fusion 360 until I found something good and blocky.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/blocks_model.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/blocks_model_mid.jpg" alt="3d model of blocks" /></a>
    
</figure>

<p>I wanted the letters to only key into their matching slot, and also stand easily when not in the box, so I modeled letter-shaped bases for them.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/bases_model.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/bases_model_mid.jpg" alt="3d model of block bases" /></a>
    
</figure>

<p>I cut the blocks out with a jigsaw and did my best to sand the inside edges smooth. Then I borrowed a friend’s <a href="https://www.shapertools.com/en-us/origin">Shaper Origin</a> CNC router to cut out the bases.</p>

<p>To make things feel a little magical, I wanted the detection mechanism to be invisible. Before gluing the blocks to their bases I embedded a magnet in each one, and I placed a Hall Effect sensor in the box under each slot. Those sensors detect the presence of a magnet, and the sensitivity was just right that they wouldn’t trigger unless the blocks were fully seated.</p>

<p>To make the box, I roughly followed <a href="https://www.familyhandyman.com/project/how-to-make-a-simple-wooden-box/">these plans I found on Family Handyman</a>. It was simple enough, and I loved being able to wrap the grain all the way around the outside.</p>

<p>For the electronics, I needed a music player which could read the state of the four Hall Effect sensors and play an amplified audio track when the button was pressed. I’ve had a <a href="https://www.sparkfun.com/sparkfun-mp3-player-shield.html">Sparkfun MP3 player shield</a> in my drawer for ages, and realized it was now or never. I’d have loved to use the <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/2217">Adafruit audio FX board</a>, but it can’t handle the input combinations I needed. I had this <a href="https://www.velleman.eu/products/view/7-w-mono-audio-amplifier-k4001/?id=9181">old mono amp</a> I must have picked up from a garage sale, but unfortunately the grounding schemes do not seem compatible between the MP3 player and the amp. I’m sure there’s some circuitry I could add to interface them, but instead I just grabbed a new <a href="https://www.sparkfun.com/sparkfun-mono-audio-amp-breakout-tpa2005d1.html">amp from Sparkfun</a>. The speaker was another part dug out from the scrap drawer. On the rear side is a DC barrel jack for power and a potentiometer for volume control. The speaker was held in place inside with a wooden bracket.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/electronics.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/electronics_mid.jpg" alt="electronics installed" /></a>
    
</figure>

<p>The slots were also cut out with the Shaper Origin, and at the last minute I decided the play button should be heart shaped. To finish the wood I sanded everything fine, wiped it with a damp cloth, then rubbed it with danish oil.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/finished.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/finished_mid.jpg" alt="finished music box" /></a>
    
</figure>

<p>Next came the dreaded task of chopping up the audio.</p>

<p>I imported the song into the free, open-source audio editing program <a href="https://www.audacityteam.org">Audacity</a> and plugged in a tempo number I found online to give some helpful snap points. I zoomed in on the start of each letter’s section and added a split where I saw the beginning of a spike in the waveform. Once I had each letter, I created multiple tracks to test and fine-tune the start and end times until all the transitions were seamless. The bass guitar ended up being the key to getting things to match, as it was thankfully steady throughout the entire song.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/audacity.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/audacity_mid.jpg" alt="chopped waveforms in Audacity" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Experimenting in Audacity</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Due to the limitations of the MP3 player shield, my best option for <a href="https://github.com/brushyfork23/love_music_box/blob/main/love.ino">the software</a> was to create an individual MP3 file for each of the 16 possible combinations. I simply converted the presence or absence of each letter into a 1 or 0, then converted that to a track name (for example, if only O and V are placed then it finds track “0110.mp3”). As a treat, when all letters are placed the entire song plays all the way through.</p>

<p>Shockingly I was able to keep this project a surprise and it made a lovely Christmas gift. My wife was initially confused about being gifted a pretty wooden rectangle, but after I explained the concept she was quite touched.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.jpg"><img src="/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box_mid.jpg" alt="music box on a shelf" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>In the end I think the craftsmanship was worthy of the recipient.</figcaption>
    
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A music box to play with the sounds of L-O-V-E.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/love_music_box/love_music_box.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Now Playing</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/01/11/now-playing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Now Playing" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/01/11/now-playing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2024/01/11/now-playing.html"><![CDATA[<p>We needed somewhere to place the sleeve for the currently-playing record. We had an IKEA picture ledge from our old apartment that just needed to be hung up. But before we got around to it, my wife came to me and mused: “Most of the time I’m listening to the radio, and I’d love to see the name of the song or artist without having to pull out my phone. Can you put a ticker of the live feed on the front of the shelf?”</p>

<p>It took less than 30 minutes to report an excited “yes!”</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/prototype.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/prototype_mid.jpg" alt="prototype" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>It's almost embarassing when the Seattle station plays Nirvana</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Our fabulous local radio station, <a href="https://kexp.org/">KEXP</a>, has a real time playlist you can query through their API. I grabbed a microcontroller, a screen, and some other bits I had on hand, and threw together a working prototype. Knowing I had some scrap wood, I decided it would be a fun constraint to build this without buying anything new.</p>

<p>Two boards were joined into a T, making a shelf with a lip to hold up the record and a face to mount the screen into. I cut a slot in the face board that the shelf board could press-fit into using a table saw.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/wood.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/wood_mid.jpg" alt="wood" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Press-fit slot cut with table saw</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/wood_with_screen.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/wood_with_screen_mid.jpg" alt="wood with screen" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Getting a feel for it in place</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>A few features added in were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A switch on the front to turn the screen on and off</li>
  <li>A hidden reed switch on the shelf to detect when it was holding a record.</li>
  <li>Two LEDs on the front which turn on when a record is detected</li>
  <li>A hidden contrast knob for the LCD</li>
  <li>The words “NOW PLAYING” etched into the wood</li>
</ul>

<p>I used a router to cut a recess so the LCD would sit flush against the front, then got everything except the front LEDs mounted, wired, and working.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/first_assembly.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/first_assembly_mid.jpg" alt="first assembly" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>I should figure out how to work with ribbon cables...</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>A friend offered to use his laser to etch the front, so we gave it a shot. This was a new technique for us, and we learned a lot about the machine and how to interact with cheap wood. In hindsight I don’t think the fill pattern works as well with the wood grain as perhaps just an outline would have.</p>

<p>I then stained the wood, glued and reassembled everything, and installed the LEDs on either side of the etched words.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/stain_and_laser.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/stain_and_laser_mid.jpg" alt="laser-etched" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Stained and laser-etched</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/stained_side.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/stained_side_mid.jpg" alt="stained side view" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Electronics are hidden from normal viewing angles</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/reed_switch.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/reed_switch_mid.jpg" alt="reed switch" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The hidden reed switch that a record presses down on</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I did unfortunately have to go buy brackets to mount this to the wall, which sadly brought the project cost up to $4. So close!</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/brackets.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/brackets_mid.jpg" alt="brackets" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The single center bracket I first tried was too bouncy</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>And that’s it!</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/with_record.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/with_record_mid.jpg" alt="with record" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Holding a record</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/with_radio.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/with_radio_mid.jpg" alt="with radio" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Showing what's on the radio</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>It’s simultaneously exactly what we need while also being pretty rough and clunky. I don’t love the screen, the etching looks dull, and the front LEDs are totally unnecessary. But it was fun to build, and it was a great way to use up some parts that would otherwise just collect dust.</p>

<p>The code is here if you’re interested: <a href="https://github.com/brushyfork23/now-playing/blob/main/now_playing.ino">github.com/brushyfork23/now-playing</a>. I wrote it quickly and never looked back, so it’s missing some key features. Overflowing text doesn’t scroll into view, and there’s some encoding mismatch so characters are often garbled. But it works well enough to answer the question “who’s playing?”</p>

<p>PS: the old picture ledge we had from our last apartment? I repurposed it and its brethren to hold shallow items in the garage.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/now_playing/garage_shelves.jpg"><img src="/assets/now_playing/garage_shelves_mid.jpg" alt="garage shelves" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Perfect size for glue and paint!</figcaption>
    
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This record display shelf also says what's on the radio.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/now_playing/now_playing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/now_playing/now_playing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Solder Dispenser</title><link href="https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/30/solder-dispenser.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solder Dispenser" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/30/solder-dispenser</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaelblackmade.com/2023/11/30/solder-dispenser.html"><![CDATA[<p>I replaced the combination work station I’ve had for years with new separated tools, and was surprised by the solution I came to for a solder dispenser.</p>

<p>The station I’m moving away from is the “<a href="https://sciplus.com/led-magnifying-work-stand-with-third-hand">LED Magnifying Work Stand With Third Hand</a>” sold by American Science &amp; Surplus:</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/solder_dispenser/station.jpg"><img src="/assets/solder_dispenser/station_small.jpg" alt="combination workstation" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>The solder dispenser is that black horizontal bar in the back.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>It’s got a lot of features, each providing a use I’ve come to rely on:</p>

<ul>
  <li>helper hands clamp</li>
  <li>gooseneck alligator clip third hand</li>
  <li>soldering iron stand</li>
  <li>brass wool holder</li>
  <li>light / magnifying glass</li>
  <li>solder dispenser</li>
</ul>

<p>But after working with it for so long, I’ve identified the tools and processes that will better serve my needs.</p>

<p>The move started when I received an <a href="https://omnifixo.com/en-us/products/of-m4-pre-order">Omnifixo M4</a> as a gift. I love this clamp set, particularly because it lets me get very precise holds easily in a way I never could with the springy gooseneck arm. It also lets me hold multiple things independently, something that was frustratingly difficult when all your clamps are fixed to the same base.</p>

<p>I clean my soldering iron tip by dragging it toward me across brass wool, which consequently sends little bits of metal flying everywhere. This <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000TGNWCS">soldering iron and brass wool holder</a> has a great domed covering that keeps the splatter contained. I also really appreciate being able to stash the iron away from my clamped workpiece.</p>

<p>I have a positionable light panel on the workbench, and I love this <a href="https://www.aliexpress.us/item/2255800088970007.html">cheap handheld magnifier</a> ($3.97 shipped when I got it), so the only missing component to be replaced was the solder dispenser.</p>

<p>I thought for a moment about buying something purpose-built, but instead I looked around the room for an axle and frame and landed on this:</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/solder_dispenser/perspective.jpg"><img src="/assets/solder_dispenser/perspective_mid.jpg" alt="two popsicle sticks shoved through slits in folded cardboard, holding solder spools" /></a>
    
    <figcaption>Two popsicle sticks and a scrap of cardboard.  That's it.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I often start with a cardboard prototype for project enclosures, but this combination of paper and popsicle sticks does what I need and seems strong enough to last.</p>

<p>I drilled holes in the ends of the sticks so I could use a safety pin to stop them from slipping out, but that turned out completely unnecessary. The press fit of the popsicle stick through a slit in the cardboard is plenty sturdy to keep things in place.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/solder_dispenser/side.jpg"><img src="/assets/solder_dispenser/side_mid.jpg" alt="side view" /></a>
    
    <figcaption></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The holes in the front stick are very useful, though, as they keep the threaded solder from getting lost on the spool.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/solder_dispenser/solder_dispenser.jpg"><img src="/assets/solder_dispenser/solder_dispenser_mid.jpg" alt="solder dispenser" /></a>
    
    <figcaption></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>While this does stay in place when the solder is pulled from it, I added some adhesive rubber feet to the bottom to give it a little extra grip. Now it can take a hefty tug and still stay put.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <a href="/assets/solder_dispenser/feet.jpg"><img src="/assets/solder_dispenser/feet_mid.jpg" alt="feet" /></a>
    
    <figcaption></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>If I had a 3D printer, I’m sure I would have made something out of plastic. It would have been irresistible. But I’m actually really thankful I don’t and didn’t. This folded piece of cardboard is tough and rigid enough that I expect this dispenser to last for many years. And when its end does come, I can just toss it in the compost and make another.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes the cardboard prototype is all you need.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/solder_dispenser/solder_dispenser.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://michaelblackmade.com/assets/solder_dispenser/solder_dispenser.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>